{
  "reference_number": "1931",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The emissions reduction goal should follow the science which is that we need to achieve net negative emissions in order to reduce\n atmospheric GHG levels to the pre-industrial state of 350ppm in order to restore the Earth's energy balance."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "It is highly likely that future supply & demand issues will drive up the price of credible international carbon units substantially and that\n domestic reductions were more likely to be achieved for a sensible price."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This must be based primarily on peer reviewed scientific climate change evidence ( and specifically NOT right wing climate change\n\n denialism or specious 'go-slow' arguments ). There are still major issues with politicians the world over thinking that somehow nature\n is listening to political spin and vested interest groups. Climate change is a physical process that responds only to physical reality viz.\n\n accumulated green house gas levels in the atmosphere. It is highly likely that we will discover that we need to move faster than we\n are to reduce emissions given the existence of dangerous feedback processes ( eg methane emissions from frozen tundra and\n undersea methane deposits; eg loss of Arctic ice cover driving rapid change in sea temperatures )."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It's a useful model. We need to be prepared for Nature to make more stringent demands on our timelines."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "Any ability to legislatively change the budgets must be based on peer reviewed scientific climate change evidence and should be\n subject to binding combined scientific and judicial review and veto."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Any ability to legislatively change the budgets must be based on peer reviewed scientific climate change evidence and should be\n\nsubject to binding combined scientific and judicial review and veto."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Note that peer reviewed scientific climate change evidence of the imperative for climate change action must take precedence. We\n\nmust avoid 'false coupling' of issues eg The National Party apparently believe that it's jobs or climate change action and use this \"fake\nlogic\" to justify taking no effective action when no effective action on climate change will lead to enormous market disruption. Human\n\nconsiderations are definitely important and efforts must be made by society collectively to help individuals or disadvantaged groups\nwith difficult transitions. For example Government funded land swaps linked to forest planting schemes may be a way of assisting\n\npeople with low lying properties escape to higher ground. We must embrace compassionate and generous approaches to solving\nthe challenges of climate change whilst always addressing the physical reality of climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We must manage with a firm eye on the physical realities of the climate change process."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "People chosen must demonstrate a clear understanding of the scientific foundation for urgent action being taken and be change\n\noriented rather than 'passive resisters' of change."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes and define it as a sub-committee process of the Climate Change Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "WE NEED TO FACE THE FACTS THAT: (1) Climate change mechanisms were well enough understood by scientists in the early 1980's\nto correctly initiate the Kyoto Protocol; (2) Right wing climate change denialism has been spectacularly effective in blocking the\n\nnecessary emissions reductions from being implemented and as a result emissions have increased since the 1991 Kyoto Protocol\nwas agreed; (3) Irresponsible political management of the climate change issue and delayed action has substantially increased the\n\nrisks to humanity of catastrophic climate change impacts occurring; (4) Temperature changes associated with the Earth's energy\nimbalance have been absorbed by the oceans and ice melt but will start to increase more rapidly as the oceans warm. There is a\n\nmaterial risk that climate change impacts will massively impact agricultural output leading to famine. Crop-growing and grazing land is\na delicate and very thin layer [only 50 cm thick] of the the ecosystem that is extremely vulnerable to minor climate change damage (\neg flooding, erosion, temperature change and drought ); (5) There is a real risk of sea level rises being dramatically larger or more\n\nrapid (or both) than the \"1-2 metres in the next 100 years\" planning guidelines communicated by the NZ Government which are\nintellectually dishonest in that they fail to state the true scale of sea level rises that could occur; (6) There is credible geological\n\nevidence showing historical sea level rises of around 10 metres being associated with only a 1.0 degree C rise in atmospheric\ntemperatures. The Paris Accord only aims to limit temperature increase to 2.0 degrees C (maybe 1.5 degrees C). The associated\n\nscale of sea level rise will result in massive destruction of valuable human-built infrastructure and significant inundation of low altitude\nagricultural land. It is very likely that the Paris Accord targets are too soft. (7) The maximum potential for sea level rises of around 70\nmetres from ice melt would be enormously destructive to human society and economies as would sea level rises of only 10-20\n\nmetres; (8) Modern advanced societies depend on stability and the long term use of assets. New Zealand will never rationally be able\nafford to rebuild Whangarei, Auckland, Tauranga, Hamilton, Palmerston North, Wellington, Christchurch, Dunedin, and Invercargill as a\n\nresult of sea level rise and inundation. Prevention will be cheaper than dealing with the consequences of climate change; (9) There is\ncredible scientific evidence for the existence of feedback processes that could swamp any ability for humanity to 'control' climate\n\nchange by emissions reductions and this should drive far greater urgency in our actions than has been evidence to date; AND\nTHEREFORE WE MUST ensure that New Zealand's climate change response truly reflects the real gravity of the climate change\nproblem. While we are a small country, leadership is a critical element of driving global progress. We must lead given the lack of global\n\nprogress. Finally, I strongly recommend that we consider the benefits of 'central bank funding mechanisms' that will enable rapid\nprogress to be made on critical projects ( eg wind farms, geothermal power stations, railway electrification, energy system upgrades,\n\npublic transport upgrades, research and development initiatives etc ) whilst allowing for the costs to be amortised across multiple\ngenerations. The use of 'quantitative easing' has precedents globally to rescue the banking system. Saving the planet from human-\n\ninduced climate change is a far more worthy goal and will result in the sort of stability that financial markets, businesses and ordinary\npeople undeniably prefer."
    }
  ]
}
